Eleanore Pettersen Architectural Collection, 1915-2010 (bulk 1950-2000)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Eleanore Pettersen Architectural Collection, 1915-2010 (bulk 1950-2000)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2003-018
218 containers; 296 cu. ft.
Eleanore K. Pettersen (1916-2003) received a Certificate in Architecture from Cooper Union for Advancement of Science and Art in 1941, and was an apprentice to Frank Lloyd Wright at Taliesin from 1941-1943. She was one of the first women licensed as an architect in the state of New Jersey in 1950, and was the first woman in New Jersey to open her own architectural office. She primarily designed residences and was also very active in professional and civic organizations. She became a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects (FAIA) in 1991. The collection consists of project files, sketches, blueprints, drawings, models, photographs, and other material relating to over 600 of Pettersen's projects as well as material relating to her participation in various professional and civic organizations. The materials in the collection range in date from 1915-2003 with the bulk of the material dating 1950-2000.
Eleanore Pettersen
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Eleanore Pettersen Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in September 2003.
Biographical Information
Eleanore K. Pettersen entered Cooper Union for Advancement of Science and Art in New York City in 1937 intent on studying painting; but, her first drafting course changed her focus and she emerged in 1941 with a Certificate in Architecture. Following Cooper Union she apprenticed with Frank Lloyd Wright at Taliesin from 1941 to 1943. After leaving the communal environment of Taliesin, where Pettersen comments that she “was never without a bandage the whole time,” she worked on various projects including the National Defense Research Committee in Princeton, NJ, the Tennessee Valley Authority, and with architect Arthur Rigolo in Clifton, New Jersey before becoming licensed as an architect in the state of New Jersey in 1950 and opening her own architectural office in 1952. Pettersen was the first woman in the state to open her own architectural office and she did so in style, renovating a 200-year-old barn in Saddle River, NJ, to be her home and office.
Over the years she employed a number of interns and apprentices (often women), preferring to hire right out of architecture school. Within a few weeks of being hired and initiated into the firm’s detail-oriented method, the new employees were assigned their own projects and were encouraged to work closely with the clients and to follow their projects through not only the design but building aspects as well. In July 1970, Pettersen formed Design Collaborative, an interior design component to her architectural firm, furthering her thorough involvement in the design process.
Although Pettersen designed a number of commercial and institutional properties, she was primarily a residential architect. Among her clients were former President Richard Nixon and jazz artist George Benson. She was also extremely proud of her involvement with the luxury town house community, Bear’s Nest, in Park Ridge, New Jersey. It was developed in phases during the 1980s and 1990s, and each of the approximately 200 units had custom design features.
She stressed a personal relationship with the clients, and this is very evident in the correspondence and writings found within her collection. An excerpt from the program Ageless Perceptions IV: Senior Women in Architecture, an exhibit held at the SOHO20 Gallery in New York City, highlights Pettersen’s devotion to architecture:
1991 will be my fortieth year as an architectural principal with my own office. Architecture has been a total commitment. If I were to make a choice all over again, the choice would be the same. Architecture has imbued me with a sense of self worth and has given me the privilege of contributing a new sense of life and meaning to my clients and their families.
Pettersen’s commitment to architecture superseded creating designs and working with clients. She also served on a number of national and local professional/civic organizations promoting architecture as a viable profession for women with her presence and accomplishments.
In 1957 she founded the Bergen County Chapter of Altrusa (a service organization for professional women), and over her decades long involvement served as president for three non-consecutive terms. She was also on several boards including: the Arts Center of Northern New Jersey; Ramapo College of New Jersey; the Mercer Community College board of directors; Young Women’s Christian Association (YWCA); and various Bergen County committees including the Bergen County Task Force of Affordable Housing.
Professionally she was just as engaged becoming a member of the American Institute of Architects (AIA) in 1954 and serving on various sub-committees. She also belonged to the New Jersey Society of Architects, the Architectural League of Northern New Jersey, and served on the boards of local architecture schools like the New Jersey Institute of Technology
Pettersen was featured in [at least] three exhibitions: Ageless Perceptions IV – Senior Women in Architecture at the SOHO20 Gallery in New York City in 1991, Eleanore Pettersen, FAIA/Four Decades (a one-woman show) at the Arts Center of Northern New Jersey in New Milford, NJ, in 1991, and Taliesin Legacy: The Independent Work of Frank Lloyd Wright Apprentices at the Pratt Manhattan Gallery in New York in 1992.
During her fifty year career Pettersen achieved a number of firsts including: the first woman recipient of the Professional Achievement Citation for Distinguished Accomplishments by Cooper Union (1965); first woman appointed by the governor to the New Jersey State Board of Architects and subsequently its first woman president (1975- 1976); first female president of the New Jersey Society of Architects (1984); and first woman elected as New Jersey’s Regional Director to the AIA Board (1986-1989).
Pettersen was named an AIA Fellow in 1991. She passed away at her Saddle River home in 2003.
Scope and Content
Pettersen’s collection encompasses over fifty years of architectural practice including project files, sketches, drawings, blueprints, models, slides and photographs representing approximately 600 designs. The collection also contains Pettersen’s personal papers including biographical information, family papers, and photographs. The materials range in date from 1915-2003 (bulk 1950-2000) and are divided into five series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Office Records, Project Records, and Artifacts and Models. See the contents list below for more detail about the individual series.
Arrangement
The Eleanore Pettersen Architecture Collection is divided into five series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Office Records, Project Records, and Art, Artifacts, Models. The series are arranged alphabetically by subject except for the Project Records. They are arranged in a Project Index alphabetically by client’s name.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
The ImageBase at Virginia Tech's Special Collections contains digital images of Pettersen's work.
Index Terms
Persons:
Pettersen, Eleanore, 1916-2003.; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959.
Corporate Names:
Eleanore Pettersen Associates.; Design Collaborative.
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.; Architects--New Jersey.; Buildings--Specifications.; Women architects--New Jersey.; Women-owned architectural firms.
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Blueprints.; Models (representations).; Photographs.
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- SERIES I: Personal Papers, 1918-2003
  The Personal Papers series contains Pettersen’s family papers, biographical information, and personal correspondence (1963-1999). The series also contains a subseries of photographs and slides.
  - SUBSERIES A: General, 1928-2003
    - (Box 1)
      - ‘Adrienne Remembered,’ eulogy, 1985
      - Biographical information, 1941-1994
      - Diploma from Cooper Union and Commencement Program, 1976
      - Correspondence, personal, 1963-1977
      - Correspondence, personal, 1981-1983
      - Correspondence, personal, 1990-1999
      - Correspondence, personal, undated
      - Estate planning, personal, 1999
      - Family Papers (Cecil Pettersen), 1928-1951
      - Family Papers, poetry of Cecil Pettersen, undated
      - Gordin, Alixie, Casting Society of America 8th Annual Artios Awards Program, 1992
      - Hejduk, John. Such Places as Memory, autographed book
      - Memo regarding will, undated
      - Memorial service, Pettersen, 2003
      - Postage stamps, 1982, undated
    - (Oversize 81)
      - Copy of a sketch featuring a young woman and a letter from Eugene Mackay, 1946
    - (Map-case 30, Drawer 1, Folder 1)
      - Artwork, Alixe Gordin
  - SUBSERIES B: Photographs/Slides, 1918-1995
    The subseries photographs/slides are divided further into Family Portraits and Photographs, Miscellaneous. The miscellaneous photographs are mostly unidentified snapshots. Major subjects present include: Altrusa meetings; Pettersen's barn/studio and pets; Pettersen's travels to visit friends; parties/gatherings; house models; Taliesin West Half Century celebration; and a visit to Frank Lloyd Wright's Grand Waikapu Country Club in Maui, Hawaii.
    - Family Portraits, 1918-1995
      - (Box 1)
        - Photographs of Pettersen, circa 1919-1995
        - Photographs, proof sheets of Pettersen portraits by Jill Krementz, undated
        - Photographs, Pettersen’s family
        - Photographs, family and friends, 1918-1929, undated
      - (Box 81)
        - Portrait of Pettersen as a baby, framed
        - Portrait of Pettersen’s father, E.A. Pettersen, undated
        - Portrait of a young woman in riding attire, undated
        - Portrait of a young woman [Pettersen?], undated
        - Portrait of a young woman [Pettersen?], undated
    - Photographs, Miscellaneous
      - (Box 10)
        - Contains photographs featuring: Altrusa meetings; Pettersen's barn/studio and pets; Pettersen's travels to visit friends; parties/gatherings; house models; Taliesin West Half Century celebration; and a visit to Frank Lloyd Wright's Grand Waikapu Country Club in Maui, Hawaii.
      - (Box 11, Container B)
        - Slides, People, 1940-1949
          - Mary Schneider, 1941
          - Ruth Brooke, 1941
          - Alixe Gordin and Pettersen, May 1948
          - Herb Princeton, September 1949
          - “Rudi,” 1947-1949
      - (Box 11, Container C)
        - Slides, 1989, 1995
          - People and scenery, 1989 (trip, boat, crocodile, friends)
          - People and scenery, 1989 (trip, boat, crocodile, friends)
      - (Box 11, Container D)
        - Slides, 1946, 1976-1989
          - Building, 1987 (Frank Lloyd Wright, desert?)
          - Colonial and Barns, 1946
          - Construction site, desert, 1989
          - Trip, Ancient ruins, 1989
          - Trip, England, 1976
          - Trip, Stonehenge, 1977
- SERIES II: Professional Papers, 1915-2002, bulk 1950-2000
  The Professional Papers series consists of material relating to Pettersen’s participation in various professional and civic organizations, material (collected by Pettersen) documenting Frank Lloyd Wright and Taliesin, various awards received by Pettersen, correspondence, and general reference files.
  - SUBSERIES A: General, 1949-2000
    - (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, professional, 1969-1990
      - Correspondence, professional, 1991-2000, undated
      - Correspondence from Virginia Tech/IAWA, 1991
      - Draft of letter to Bill Brown III (re: NJSE and architectural archives), undated
      - Draft of Chapter III (unidentified project), undated
      - Lecture notes, Altrusa (2 sets), undated
      - Lecture notes on architecture, 1989-1993
      - Lecture notes on architecture, undated
      - Lecture notes and slides on architecture, undated
      - Lecture script ‘How to sell a haunted house’ for Bergen county Consortium for teacher of the gifted, 1995
      - Lecture notes on Residential Architecture, 1920s-1990s, circa 1990
      - Lecture Slides, Pettersen Houses, undated
      - Lecture Notes on Frank Lloyd Wright (5 sets), 1979, undated
      - Lecture, 'Wright Houses and Building,' undated
      - Letters of Recommendation for EKP, 1949
      - Letters of Recommendation by EKP, 1950-1955, 1967-1978
      - Presentation slides, 1949-1922 (see box 11 below)
      - Reference Files
        - AIA Newsletter “Memo,” 1980-1981, 1986
        - Architects’ Office Management and Administration Report, 1990 [newsletter]
        - Bergen County directory of organizations for women, 1980
        - Clippings from House Beautiful, 1967
        - Georgia, roster of registered architects, 1956
        - Holder, Gus. Booklet “Interiors that Charm,” undated
        - Mies van der Rohe, Ludwig. Article, 1992
        - Montim, R. M. album, curriculum vitae and completed project photos, 1988
        - National Fallout shelter Design Competition Awards, 1967
        - National Park Service Alumnae Association newsletter “The Bulletin,” 1981-1994
        - New Jersey State Women’s Committee, clippings and fliers, 1973-1996
        - “Notebook of Enterprising Women,” business directory, 1986
        - Ostrom, Barbara, clippings, 1990
        - Postcards, undated
        - Ramapo College, booklets and newsletter, 1985-1992
        - Rose, James (landscape architect), articles, 1987-1992
        - Saddle River, NJ, clippings on housing and zoning, 1987-1995
        - Wilmington Station Rehabilitation (including profile of Pettersen’s office), 1977
        - Women in Architecture, clippings and book chapter, 1977-1992
        - Women’s Rights Information center, clippings and newsletters, 1982-1983
    - (Box 77)
      - State licenses to practice architecture, Georgia, 1956
      - State licenses to practice architecture, Massachusetts, 1974
      - State licenses to practice architecture, New York, 1974
      - State licenses to practice architecture, North Carolina, 1958 (2)
    - (Box 85)
      - AIA, certificate of membership, 1954
      - Member, Board of Architects, New Jersey, 1973
      - State license to practice architecture, Connecticut, 1961
      - State license to practice architecture, New Jersey, 1950
    - (Box 87)
      - Cooper Union, diploma, 1941
      - National Council of Architectural Registration Boards, Standard Junior Examination, 1950
    - (Box 11, Container C)
      - Presentations Slides
        - Buildings, 1976
        - Buildings, undated (not Pettersen)
        - Buildings, interiors, undated
        - Buildings, 1992
        - Lecture slides, Pettersen portrait, undated
        - East Hampton, 1949, 1958, 1971, 1973
  - SUBSERIES B: Associations and Committees, 1955-2002
    Pettersen was active locally and nationally in professional organizations, as a member of the New Jersey Society of Architects and the American Institute of Architects, and in civic organizations, as a member of the Altrusa Club, YWCA, and the New Jersey State Council on the Arts. She was also involved in various local groups/projects, such as the Housing Development Corporation of Bergen County, Bergen Community College Women’s Institute Advisory Council, and the Uniform Construction Code Advisory Board. Materials relating to these activities primarily include minutes, correspondence, agendas, reports, notes, and printed material.
    - (Box 1)
      - Altrusa Club of Bergen County, 1978, 1980
      - Altrusa Club of Bergen County, 1978-1981
      - [Altrusa International], 1979-1982
      - Altrusa, Masters, Year Book, 1978-1980
      - Altrusa, Membership Bank, 1976-1977
      - Altrusa Club - Miscellaneous Papers, Newspaper Clippings
      - ACP: Feasibility Study for a 4-Year College in Bergen co., New Jersey by Architects Associated for College Planning (ACP), 1967
      - AIA, Architectural Education Initiative, 1987-1988
      - AIA, Committee on Design, Design Commission, 1986-1988
      - AIA, Convention, 1982-1984
      - AIA, Board of Directors, minutes, December 1984
    - (Box 2)
      - AIA, Board of Directors, Minutes, Correspondence, 1986-1987
      - AIA, Board of Directors, Correspondence and Meeting Information, 1987
      - AIA, General Information, 1983-1985
      - AIA, Housing Committee Correspondence, 1991
      - AIA, Recommendation letters for Jay Iselin to be the Public Director of AIA Board, 2001
      - AIA, Regional Director, brochures and notes on committee membership and fund raising, 1988
      - AIA, Regional Director, reports, correspondence, NJSA/AIA firm directory, 1987-1989
      - AIA, reports, 1987-1988
      - AIA: Women in Architecture Task Force, 1975-1980
      - Architecture Advisory Commission, Minutes, 1984
      - Art Center of Northern New Jersey Board, 1997
      - Bergen Community College Women's Institute Advisory Council, 1977-1978
      - Bergen County - Affordable Housing Task Force, 1990-1992
      - Bergen County - Art Auction, November 1979
      - Bill Bradley for U.S. Senate, Advisory Council, 1984-1985
      - Cases for CASA (Cart Appointed Special Advocate) Recognition, 1997
      - Cooper Union, 1955, 1957, 1967, 1973-1979
      - Cooper Union, 1979-1981
      - Cooper Union Alumni Association, 2000
      - Cooper Union Trustees meeting and school catalog, 1983
      - Housing Development Corporation of Bergen County, Affordable House, 1977-1981 (2 folders)
      - Housing Development Corporation of Bergen County, 1980-1982 (3 folders)
      - Housing Development Corporation of Bergen County, 1982-1986 (4 folders)
      - [Housing Development Corporation of Bergen County], 1987
      - Interfaith Forum on Religion, Art, and Architecture (IFRAA), 1984, 1986-1987
      - IFRAA, 1987-1989 (2 folders)
      - Mercer County Community College, Board of Directors, handbook and correspondence, 1980-1984
      - New Jersey Institute of Technology, correspondence, 1979-1981
      - New Jersey School of Architecture (at New Jersey Institute of Technology), Advisory Board, 2001-2002
    - (Box 3)
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1979-1980 (3 folders)
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1980-1981 (2 folders)
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1982
      - New Jersey Society of Architects (NJSA), Annual Meetings, Budgets, Building Codes, 1980-1981
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1981-1982, 1984-1985 (2 folders)
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1982-1986
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1983-1984
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Annual Conference, 1984
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Treasurer's Report, 1985
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, 1985-1986 (3 folders)
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Adult Education Committee, 1971
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Amicus Brief, Comments of Code, Women in Architecture, 1985-1986
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Continuing Education, 1980
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Schinnerer Speech: A New Vista of Architect’s Legal Responsibilities, 1960
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Executive Committee Information, April 1987
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Executive Committee Information, May 1987
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, Executive Committee Information, June 1987
      - New Jersey State Board of Architects, Minutes, 1984-1985
      - New Jersey State Board of Architects, Minutes, 1987
      - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, 1985-1987
      - Ramapo State College, 1985-1986
      - Ramapo State College, Board of Directors Calendar and Address List, 1992
      - Taliesin, Correspondence with Edgar Tafel and others, 1970-1998, undated
      - Taliesin, Fellows' Alumni Events, 1986-1992
      - Taliesin, The Taliesin Fellowship, 1932-1982, directory
      - Turnpike Regional Environment Enrichment, beginning 1985
      - [Uniform Construction Code Advisory Board], 1977-1978 (2 folders)
      - Uniform Construction Appeal Board, Saddle River, beginning 1979, Vasilios Saites, 1979
      - Uniform Construction Appeal Board, Saddle River, beginning 1979, Samuel E. Jensen, Jr., 1979
      - Uniform Construction Appeal Board, Saddle River, beginning 1979, Daniel Melehan, 1979
      - Uniform Construction Appeal Board, Saddle River, beginning 1979, Eleanore Pettersen, 1977-1979
      - Uniform Construction Appeal Board, Appeal Board Hearing, Dr. John Winn, 1981
      - YMCA-YWCA, 1975-1982
      - YWCA Board of Trustees, 1983-1985
    - (Box 11, container C)
      - Slides
        - Altrusa
          - Meeting [Altrusa?], 1993
          - Women by Lake, 1993
          - Conference, 1993
          - Installation, 1994
          - Altrusa BC, February 1995
          - Scranton conference, May election, 1995
  - SUBSERIES C: Awards, 1957-2002
    Professional and civic awards presented to Pettersen.
    - (Box 4)
      - AIA, Architects League of Northern New Jersey - Appreciation, Lifetime Award, 1997, 1999
      - AIA, Fellowship Nomination, 1991 Binder One
      - AIA, Fellowship Nomination, 1991 Binder Two
      - AIA, Fellowship Nomination, 1991, material inserted in AIA Fellowship binder, 1991
      - AIA, Fellowship, correspondence, 1991
      - AIA, Certificate of Fellowship, 1991
      - Altrusa Club, 'A Salute to Eleanore Pettersen, F.A.I.A,' 2000
      - Arts Center of Northern New Jersey, Artist Ball honoring Eleanore Pettersen, 1991
      - Borough of Ramsey, Certificate of Appreciation, 1983
      - Brandeis University National Women's Committee, bookplate given in honor of Pettersen, 1993
      - Casas for CASA, appreciation plaque, 1997
      - Child Care Center, Dr. David Goldberg, Appreciations Award, 1985
      - Cooper Union, Augustus St. Gaudens Award for Professional Achievement, 1994
      - Cooper Union, membership in The Golden Legion, 1991
      - Cooper Union, Professional Achievement, 1965
      - Cooper Union, membership in The Society of 1859, 2002
      - County of Bergen, New Jersey, Certificates of Commendation, 1993
      - Finalist, Entrepreneur of the Year Award, 1992
      - Finalist, Entrepreneur of the Year Award, 1993
      - Girl Scouts Outstanding Achievement, 1987
      - Kathryn Miller Award to Outstanding Women active in Women's Rights Issues in Bergen County, 1989
      - New Jersey Department of Community Affairs, Certificate of Appreciation, 1996
      - New Jersey Institute of Technology, Certificate of Appreciation, 1997
      - New Jersey Women of Achievement, 1995
      - Pioneer Women of the 1990s, 1991
      - Ramapo College, Recognition, 1994, undated
      - Saddle River, Mayor's Award, 1994
      - Socially Responsible 1992 Entrepreneur of the Year Award, finalist, 1992
      - Women’s Rights Information Center, “Elizabeth Cady Stanton ‘The World is Moving’ Award,” 1991
      - Women's Rights Information Center, Turning Point Person, 1999
    - (Box 76)
      - Cooper Union, professional achievement citation, 1965
      - New Jersey, member Energy Crisis Study Commission, 1974
      - New Jersey, member Energy Crisis Study Commission, 1974
      - Women's Rights Information Center "Turning Point Person," 1999
    - (Box 78)
      - AIA, certificate of appreciation, 1989 Design Commission
      - Altrusa Club of Bergen County, 1957
      - Arts Center of Northern New Jersey, Patron of the ARTS award, 1991
      - New Jersey, Assembly Commendation, 1992
      - New Jersey, Assembly Resolution, March 1992 observed as "Women's History Month"